Pablo Mas

GitHub LinkedIn

PhD candidate specialized in machine learning for drug discovery, with an emphasis on improving exploration and exploitation during lead optimization. Conducting my research within the Theoretical Chemistry Group at ENS-PSL and the Integrated Drug Discovery team at Sanofi. I am also pursuing an MBA at the Collège des Ingénieurs and teaching at ENS-PSL and Le Wagon bootcamp.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD

10/2022 - Present

École Normale Supérieure (ENS Ulm)

Paris, France

 Conducted research on machine learning applications in drug discovery and theoretical chemistry, in collaboration with Sanofi. Under the supervision of Pr. Rodolphe Vuilleumier (ENS) and Dr. Marc Bianciotto (Sanofi).

Master of Business Administration - MBA

01/2023 — Present

Collège des Ingénieurs (CDI Paris)

Paris, France

Paris, France

Selective MBA program designed for top graduates from leading French Engineering Schools.

Master of Science - MSc BME Paris - PSL University 09/2021 - 09/2022

 Relevant courses: Deep learning and neurosciences - Deep learning and neurocomputational projects - Quantification for Neuroimaging - Machine Learning for Bioimaging

Master of Science ("Diplôme d'ingénieur") - MSc

09/2018 - 09/2021

ESPCI Paris

Paris, France

 Biotechnology specialization (3rd year): Systems biology and neurobiology - Biochemistry and molecular biotechnology - Deep learning - Statistical learning - Advanced analytical chemistry

Bachelor of Science - BSc 09/2016 - 09/2018

Sorbonne University

Paris, France

• Dual bachelor's degree with majors in physics and chemistry.

EXPERIENCE

Research scientist (CIFRE PhD)

10/2022 - Present

Paris, France

- Developed rational exploration and exploitation strategies for molecule prioritization during the lead optimization phase, supported by a comprehensive toolkit for medicinal chemists.
- Simulated active-learning based selection scenarios on legacy drug discovery projects.
- Developed QSAR/QSPR models in low and high data regimes.

Research intern 02/2022 - 09/2022

Aramis Lab (INRIA & Paris Brain Institute)

Paris, France

 Developed deep learning algorithms using graph neural networks for automated segmentation of peptide accumulation in whole-slide images, enabling improved stratification of Alzheimer's disease patients.

Research intern 04/2021 - 08/2021

LSABM (ESPCI Paris - PSL)

Paris, France

 Developed a LC-MS method to detect mustard gas-modified DNA traces in biological samples, in collaboration with the French Defence Procurement Agency.

Analytical scientist intern

Phenix Lab (CNRS)

Data analyst intern

07/2020 - 12/2020

Adocia Lyon, France

• Developed and characterized (via HPLC and NMR) a protective hydrogel for islets of Langerhans (beta cells) as part of a cell therapy project aimed at creating an artificial pancreas.

Research intern 06/2018 - 08/2018

Investigated water dynamics in 15th-century paintings through NMR relaxometry, X-ray, and IR spectroscopy.

05/2017 - 08/2017

Paris, France

Development Alternatives Incorporated

Washington DC, USA

 Developed data visualization dashboards and contributed to a report for the Aspen Institute: "A Global Opportunity: Get Youth Working".

PUBLICATIONS

Gkeka, P.; Llompart, P.; Amaning, K.; Bianciotto, M.; Filoche-Romme, B.; Foricher, Y.; Mas, P.; Papin, D.; Rameau, J.-P.; Schio, L.; Marcou, G.; Varnek, A.; Moussaid, M. Harnessing Medicinal Chemical Intuition from Collective Intelligence. 2024. https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-4365958/v1. (under review)

Bailey, M.; Moayedpour, S.; Li, R.; Corrochano-Navarro, A.; Kötter, A.; Kogler-Anele, L.; Riahi, S.; Grebner, C.; Hessler, G.; Matter, H.; Bianciotto, M.; Mas, P.; Bar-Joseph, Z.; Jager, S. Deep Batch Active Learning for Drug Discovery. eLife 2024. https://doi.org/10.7554/elife.89679.2.

Moayedpour, S.; Corrochano-Navarro, A.; Sahneh, F.; Noroozizadeh, S.; Koetter, A.; Vymetal, J.; Kogler-Anele, L.; Mas, P.; Jangjou, Y.; Li, S.; Bailey, M.; Bianciotto, M.; Matter, H.; Grebner, C.; Hessler, G.; Bar-Joseph, Z.; Jager, S. Many-Shot In-Context Learning for Molecular Inverse Design arXiv 2024. https://doi.org/10.48550/arxiv.2407.19089.

Jimenez, G.; Mas, P.; Kar, A.; Peyrache, J.; Ingrassia, L.; Boluda, S.; Delatour, B.; Stimmer, L.; Racoceanu, D. A Meta-Graph Approach for Analyzing Whole Slide Histopathological Images of Human Brain Tissue with Alzheimer's Disease Biomarkers. Med. Imaging 2023: Digit. Comput. Pathol. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2657475.

CONFERENCES

EuroQSAR 2024 Barcelona, Spain	09/2024
CS3 - Strasbourg Summer School in Cheminformatics Strasbourg, France	06/2024
MLSS - Machine Learning Summer School Okinawa, Japan	03/2024
6th Artificial Intelligence in Chemistry Symposium Cambridge, UK	09/2023
GGMM - Young Modellers Conference Toulouse, France	05/2023

09/2023 - Present

Elaborated and supervised data challenges for the "AI in Chemistry" graduate course, hosted on ENS's data challenge platform.

- 2023 challenge: Predicting molecule-protein interaction for drug discovery.
- 2024 challenge: ADMET property prediction for drug discovery.

Le Wagon Bootcamp 09/2021 — Present

- Delivered machine learning as well as deep learning courses to 250+ students.
- Supervised final bootcamp projects.

École Normale Supérieure (ENS Ulm)

SKILLS

TEACHING

ToolsPython (scikit-learn, PyTorch, Tensorflow, RDKit, deepchem...), Git, AWS, Matlab, SQL, AWS MEXCommunicationFrench (native), English (fluent - C1 level), Spanish (intermediate - B1 level)

EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- Treasurer of the ESPCI Paris PSL student's office, in charge of a 150 000€ budget.
- External Relations Officer of the ESPCI Paris PSL sports union.
- Sports: Handball (15 years, two-time high-school champion of Morocco), Diving (PADI 2), Skiing, Squash.